<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-11-13T14:10:01+05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Larissa Zhou</title><subtitle></subtitle><entry><title type="html">How to Figure Out the Real Reason You’re Stuck</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2025/11/13/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to Figure Out the Real Reason You’re Stuck" /><published>2025-11-13T09:00:00+05:00</published><updated>2025-11-13T09:00:00+05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2025/11/defender-value</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2025/11/13/"><![CDATA[<p>Have you ever found yourself doing something that you really want to stop doing, but you keep going anyways?</p>

<p>A few examples:</p>
<ul>
  <li>R is bored working on his current company but is reluctant to start something new</li>
  <li>Z continues putting in the hours at a company that irritates her morals</li>
  <li>B wants to feel content in his business but is always anxiously plotting for the next big win</li>
</ul>

<p>Usually, people will conclude that they’re not very disciplined. Not disciplined enough to start a new business, not disciplined enough to steer the project in a more fulfilling direction, not disciplined enough to find peace in the present moment.</p>

<p>But being trapped in these cycles aren’t really about insufficient willpower or motivation. They are about something much deeper.</p>

<font size="5"> **The Real Reason We Get Stuck** </font>

<p>We say we want freedom, creativity, rest, but then find ourselves doing the opposite. That’s usually a sign of a <em>Defender Value</em>: a hidden value quietly protecting something important, like safety, belonging, or approval.</p>

<p>I put together this short worksheet called <strong>Find Your Defender Value</strong>. It’s a 10-minute reflection to help you spot what your patterns are really protecting.</p>

<div style="text-align: center; margin-top: 20px;">
<a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1QkLEJVf3erxl8i2AicyLP2ZF6PWRbg0wXoiJUe8nV9E/copy" target="_blank" style="text-decoration: none;">
<button style="background-color: #222; color: #00cc66; padding: 10px 20px; border: none; border-radius: 6px; cursor: pointer; font-size: 16px;">
Get My “Find Your Defender Value” Worksheet </button> </a> </div>
<p><br /></p>

<font size="5"> **Why This Matters** </font>

<p>Every behavior makes sense in context. It was your best attempt to meet a real need. By understanding these patterns, you can begin to update the old contracts that keep them in charge and create a life that aligns with your true values.</p>

<p>If you identified the pattern and want to shift it, then <a href="https://larissazhou.github.io/apply.html" target="_blank">apply for a free strategy session with me</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="worksheet" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Have you ever found yourself doing something that you really want to stop doing, but you keep going anyways?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Case Study: Thomas Is No Longer Afraid Of Interpersonal Conflict</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2025/10/30/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Case Study: Thomas Is No Longer Afraid Of Interpersonal Conflict" /><published>2025-10-30T09:00:00+05:00</published><updated>2025-10-30T09:00:00+05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2025/10/case-study-thomas</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2025/10/30/"><![CDATA[<p><em>Thomas is a computer scientist and an entrepreneur. He worked with me 1-on-1 for a year.
For privacy reasons, Thomas’s last name has been omitted, but his story and experiences are shared here with his full permission.</em></p>

<p><strong><font size="5"> What made you want to work with Larissa? </font></strong></p>

<p>When I first started working with Larissa, I was struggling with various kinds of interpersonal conflicts. I think in particular, I was struggling the most with my own tendencies to please people and to seek approval. I wasn’t feeling secure about expressing my needs, expressing my ideas and conflicts. And that had taken a very heavy toll on my leadership role at the company I’d co-founded.</p>

<p><strong><font size="5"> What was your biggest hesitation? </font></strong></p>

<p>I wasn’t sure about the prospect of me actually fixing these issues because they have been with me for a very long time. Over many years, I have sought help in different forms and I felt like I didn’t really get to the bottom of it. I wasn’t sure if these sessions that I would be doing with Larissa would change things significantly.</p>

<p><strong><font size="5"> What results have you achieved? </font></strong></p>

<p>Since working with Larissa, I have become much more capable of handling interpersonal conflicts, both at work and in my personal life.</p>

<p style="font-size: 1.2em; margin-left: 40px;"> I’ve become much more comfortable standing up for my needs and desires, my beliefs and my opinions in heated situations, where there are loaded emotions and complicated feelings and challenging language being exchanged. </p>

<p>Besides, I have also observed a heightened awareness towards myself – awareness towards my own feelings, my thoughts, my thought processes and patterns, and my underlying beliefs.</p>

<p><strong>Ultimately, I am now more of a master of my internal reality. That’s a very empowered kind of feeling.</strong></p>

<p><strong><font size="5"> What was the experience like? </font></strong></p>

<p>I have realized that coming out of various practices and frameworks and lessons in sessions with Larissa that:</p>

<ul>
  <li>I can change my underlying beliefs</li>
  <li>that I can be in control</li>
  <li>that I can change how I handle difficult situations</li>
</ul>

<p>The most helpful thing that I took away was a combination of two things: self compassion and the idea of boundaries. Coming from an Asian background, I can say that boundaries, in my upbringing and in the culture that I grew up in, weren’t really a thing. From these sessions with Larissa, what I realized is that if I get to set a healthy boundary, I then get to be responsible for what’s on my side of the fence. I get to be responsible, and I am responsible, for my own thought process, my own feelings, my beliefs which are driving my behavior. And that’s a very empowered kind of feeling, because I get to accept them as where I stand in terms of my internal reality and I get to choose how I would think differently next time going into similar situations and that ultimately drives change.</p>

<p>Self-compassion comes in here in the sense of being compassionate with myself, being accepting, being inquisitive, being curious, without blaming, without judging, with a lot of patience, with a lot of acceptance. That’s the key to driving real change.</p>

<p><strong><font size="5"> What would have happened if you hadn’t worked with Larissa? </font></strong></p>

<p>I want to state that counterfactuals are tricky but I would say that if I didn’t work with Larissa, it is plausible that I am still struggling with the same set of issues. I will be still going into interpersonal conflicts and heated situations and still be using my old ways of dealing with people and expressing myself, which are problematic and not exactly problem solving in getting the ball rolling. And I do not envy that person. I could not imagine myself wanting to be in that version of the universe. I would very much rather that I had worked with Larissa. I have experienced these changes. And I am now walking as a new person doing things differently, and feeling much, much better and in control.</p>

<p><strong><font size="5"> Do you recommend working with Larissa? </font></strong></p>

<p>I think you should work with Larissa if, speaking from my own experience, you’re having similar issues that I had before. Issues such as, you would find yourself going into interpersonal conflicts where there are things at stake that are really important to you and you find yourself walking out of the interaction not expressing what you really wanted to express, what you really believed in. Moreover, you would be judging yourself harshly. You would find yourself generally practicing a pretty heavy filter on what you say and what you would not say, policing yourself really hard, pushing yourself really hard. And then over time, maybe you realize that that’s no longer serving you, you don’t exactly know why you do it but you can’t help but do it, and you also don’t know how to change it. I have experienced fundamental changes and I would recommend working with Larissa if you have similar kinds of issues that I had.</p>

<p align="center">🪷</p>
<p>If you want to learn how to navigate hard conversations with investors, co-founders, employees, friends, or family with integrity and power, let’s talk.</p>

<font size="5">
<p align="center">
  <a href="https://larissazhou.github.io/apply.html">Apply for a free strategy session</a>
</p></font>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="case study" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Thomas is a computer scientist and an entrepreneur. He worked with me 1-on-1 for a year. For privacy reasons, Thomas’s last name has been omitted, but his story and experiences are shared here with his full permission.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Case Study: Zach Broke Into the Food Industry With a CS Degree</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2025/10/22/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Case Study: Zach Broke Into the Food Industry With a CS Degree" /><published>2025-10-22T09:00:00+05:00</published><updated>2025-10-22T09:00:00+05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2025/10/case-study-zach</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2025/10/22/"><![CDATA[<p><em><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/zachary-schulz-/" target="_blank">Zach Schulz</a> is a computer scientist turned food applications chef. He worked with me 1-on-1 for a year.</em></p>

<font size="5"> What made you want to work with Larissa? </font>

<p>I was working in a completely different field. I didn’t really like what I was doing, but at the same time I didn’t know what I wanted to do and I didn’t know how I could even change what I was doing. So I felt very stagnant. I was concerned about not having a clear goal in place for my career.</p>

<font size="5"> What was your biggest hesitation? </font>

<p>I had also never done coaching before and I wasn’t sure if it was the right choice for getting me out of the rut I felt like I was in.</p>

<font size="5"> What specific results have you achieved? </font>

<p><strong>I’ve made a huge career change.</strong> I started out working in computer science and now I’m working in food science.</p>

<ul>
  <li>I’ve already had two paid jobs in food science.</li>
  <li>I built a great network of people in the food industry.</li>
  <li>I’ve gotten a lot more comfortable advocating for myself.</li>
</ul>

<p>Overall, <strong>I just feel a lot more confident</strong> in my ability to go after my goals.</p>

<font size="5"> What was the experience like? </font>

<p>In the first few sessions of working with Larissa, what I like most about her style is that she would ask very direct questions. At that time, I kind of lost touch with what really motivated me and what I was truly interested in. And that was in part due to influences in my life like school and my parents. Larissa would ask questions in such a way that would cut out these external voices and help me get back in touch with these things.</p>

<p>Something that Larissa and I did that helped me land my first job in a completely new industry was change my job search strategy. Before I started coaching, I was applying to a bunch of different places just submitting online forms and I never really heard back from anyone. But Larissa encouraged me to narrow down my search to just a few companies that I was really interested in, and I spent a lot of time working on the applications for these. I personalized them to each company and after submitting them, I would follow up with either the recruiter or someone who worked at the company to make sure that application was seen and that really helped me get responses to my applications and eventually get interviews and eventually a job.</p>

<p>Something that helped with my self-advocacy was when I was stuck with something at my job and I wanted to bring something up with my manager. Larissa would give me ideas on what to say or how to phrase it and she would also give me examples of what could be said to her response to those things. So I would feel more comfortable approaching my boss.</p>

<font size="5"> What would have happened if you hadn’t worked with Larissa?</font>

<p>If I hadn’t worked with Larissa, I think I would have spent a lot more time treading water in the computer science industry. Before I started coaching, I felt that I hadn’t explored computer science enough to know if it was for me. And so I think I would have spent at least several years kind of trying different jobs before realizing that I really needed to make a career change. Another thing I would have done is I probably would have gone back to school to get a degree in food science. Because before coaching, I didn’t realize that I already had what it took to get an entry level position in a new industry.</p>

<font size="5"> Do you recommend working with Larissa?</font>

<p>I think you should work with Larissa if you feel stuck in your current career even if you don’t know what you want to do or you’re worried it’s impossible to make a change. I think it’s worth trying coaching. Something else that’s helpful is being open to changing how you approach things and also being willing to put in the time to get results.</p>

<p align="center">🪷</p>
<p>If you are (or know) a young person ready to build a career with purpose, direction, and curiosity, let’s talk.</p>

<font size="5">
<p align="center">
  <a href="https://larissazhou.github.io/apply.html">Apply for a free strategy session</a>
</p></font>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="case study" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Zach Schulz is a computer scientist turned food applications chef. He worked with me 1-on-1 for a year.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ruthless Systems for Thriving: Lessons from Alone Australia S1</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2025/09/29/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ruthless Systems for Thriving: Lessons from Alone Australia S1" /><published>2025-09-29T09:00:00+05:00</published><updated>2025-09-29T09:00:00+05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2025/09/survival-triangle</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2025/09/29/"><![CDATA[<p>On the first season of Alone Australia, one of the participants, Michael, mentioned this thing called the Survival Triangle, which lays out the 3 things – <strong>hope, a plan, and work</strong> – necessary for survival.</p>

<p><img src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5823315b29687f569418dd0d/1561669583725-SZJ0KSC3I7FPAX2VBFND/IMG_0033.jpg?format=2500w" alt="John Hudson's Survival Triangle" />
(Credit: <a href="https://www.johnhudsonsurvival.com/field-notes/2019/6/27/the-survival-triangle">John Hudson’s Survival Triangle</a>)</p>

<p>As season one narrowed down to 3 contestants, it was uncanny how well the Survival Triangle explained why each of them were there.</p>

<p>Take Michael, who is deeply religious. He didn’t have much in terms of a plan and work. But faith in God kept him mentally committed. He lasted 30 days! Eating weeds!</p>

<p>Then there is Mike, who I call ruthlessly efficient. (By the way, has anyone ever named their kid Ruth Leslie? It’s a pretty badass name.) He was constantly optimizing his systems and looking for problems to solve. For example, one contestant who was lucky enough to catch an eel early on found it so fatty and disgusting that she almost hoped that she wouldn’t catch another one. When Mike encountered the same issue, his response was, right on, let’s build a smoker to improve the taste.</p>

<p>Gina seemed to have a healthy balance of all three vertices of the triangle. She’d endured the death of her infant daughter years earlier and was mentally prepared for hitting rock bottom. She had plenty of practical skills. She had faith that Mother Nature would take care of her. And because of that, she seemed to be adapting her plans organically, in harmony, with nature.</p>

<p>In the end, it came down to Mike and Gina. I found myself rooting for Mike, who put so much raw effort into his systems.  He built a freakin’ canoe, for heaven’s sake. However, Gina had luck on her side. While zoning out on a log after a midnight pee, a wallaby ambled by. She lunged at it instinctively and became the only contestant on the show to catch non-fish protein. Whereas Mike, poor Mike, built not one, but <em>two</em> traps, for the neighborhood pademelon, only for it to escape multiple times.</p>

<p>The Survival Triangle stuck in my mind because it maps neatly onto the different buckets of support I provide to clients as a career coach. Here’s how it’s shown up recently in my coaching:</p>

<p>1) X felt it was time to make a move. In the past, the next step seemed to be driven by luck. A pretty good opportunity would fall into his lap, and he had the discernment to run with it. But, according to X, “luck isn’t a process.” And what if he wanted something greater than what luck could deliver? We agreed to work together to strengthen his Survival Triangle. We’ll work on <strong>hope</strong> by tackling his lack of confidence, create <strong>a plan</strong> to map out his transition, and carve out time for the <strong>work</strong> of building his next move. He won’t need to wait for luck. He’s creating his own opportunities.</p>

<p>2) When B and I first started working together 6 months ago, she vacillated between excitement and hopelessness at how she could ever create the work and life that she wanted. When she was overwhelmed by hopelessness, her ability to plan or take action shut down completely. So, we focused first on <strong>hope</strong>, dismantling self-limiting beliefs that told her how she couldn’t have the life she wanted. Then, we optimized her <strong>work</strong> by co-creating workflows and systems that let her get more done in less time. At our most recent quarterly debrief, she was lit up, excited about all the things that she thought were out of reach that she’s finally allowing herself to pursue. Now, with those pieces in place, we’re focusing on the <strong>plan</strong> – setting ambitious, concrete goals to channel her energy in the right direction. She just committed to another 3 months of coaching to make it happen.</p>

<p>3) When I first spoke to P, he waxed on about the grand plans he would like to pursue and, in the same breath, concluded with, “But I’ll probably go back to my old, unsatisfying job after this sabbatical.” When I pointed out this curious “I’d like to do this, but I will probably do that” phenomenon, we uncovered that he had cultivated a kind of apathy towards his dreams as a defense mechanism. The logic was, If you don’t let yourself hope, you can’t be disappointed. But how can you pursue something that you won’t even let yourself imagine is possible? If we were to work together, I’d want to focus on strengthening his <strong>hope</strong> vertex first. That would mean helping him reconnect with the excitement of his big ambitions and start to believe they’re possible. From there, we’d co-create <strong>a plan</strong> to break those big goals into smaller, actionable steps, and build momentum through consistent, focused <strong>work</strong>. The goal would be to help him stop holding back and start moving toward the life he really wants.</p>

<p>Thriving in the great wilderness of one’s lifelong career requires the same three elements: hope, a plan, and work. 1:1 coaching is the fastest way to build the systems and mindset you need to succeed. If you’re ready to strengthen your Survival Triangle, <a href="https://larissazhou.github.io/apply.html">apply for a strategy session</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="general" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[On the first season of Alone Australia, one of the participants, Michael, mentioned this thing called the Survival Triangle, which lays out the 3 things – hope, a plan, and work – necessary for survival.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On Career Planning, Impending Motherhood, and the Stew</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2025/08/26/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Career Planning, Impending Motherhood, and the Stew" /><published>2025-08-26T09:00:00+05:00</published><updated>2025-08-26T09:00:00+05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2025/08/motherhood-stew</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2025/08/26/"><![CDATA[<p>Last week, I had two coaching conversations in which both women mentioned the words “motherhood” and “stew” in the same breath. What were the chances?!</p>

<p>By many measures, these women felt that they had good jobs. They’ve been thinking about moving on to something different, and an earlier version of themselves knew how to move onto the next thing. But when they think about having a baby, they get the sense that maybe what they want of their jobs will be different, but they’re also not sure exactly how it’ll be different. The result is that they’ve been stuck, neither doubling down nor moving on, in a stew of uncertainty. The impact of staying in the stew is that, as huge changes take place in their personal lives, they’re not proactively building a professional container that will support them as a mother.</p>

<p>These two conversations got me thinking about the various stews that I swam in over the past two years as I became a mother. One poignant period involved a lot of denial stew. In early pregnancy, I was delighted and happy just to stay pregnant, after a short-lived bout of pregnancy and miscarriage that shook my faith in my reproductive capabilities. A few months in, my career coach asked me, so how are your sabbatical and career goals changing now that there’s a baby on the way? I distinctly remember sitting in my Airbnb in Lima, Peru, looking out the window at the ocean waves that I wasn’t going to be surfing after all, and giving her some blah blah blah. She then asked, no really, how will your plans change? She pointed out that my plans to get a number of professional mountain guide certifications during my sabbatical were quite impossible while pregnant. That’s when I realized that the reason I was pregnant and hormonal and crying in an Airbnb in Peru is the same reason that I hadn’t updated my career parameters. I had made the Peru plans before I got pregnant, had wanted to still be as hard charging in pregnancy and motherhood, and so I just kept going, hard-headedly refusing to take reality into account.</p>

<p>That conversation with my coach was a come-to-Jesus moment for me. I saw the cost of denial and decided it wasn’t ok. But taking reality into account was harder than I anticipated. First of all, reality kept changing. What I wanted, desired, accepted, and had capacity for changed constantly throughout pregnancy and post-partum. A year after my child’s birth, things are still changing, although the rate of change has slowed.</p>

<p>In my conversation with one of the lovely stewy women, we brainstormed what it would look like to use extrapolation as a planning strategy. Extrapolate how we’d likely feel and want based on what we knew about ourselves and learning from friends ahead of us on the motherhood journey. And then make career decisions based on those likelihoods. But as the philosopher <a href="https://lapaul.org/papers/whatCantExpect.pdf">LA Paul describes</a>, matrescence is an epistemological transformative experience:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“…since having one’s own child is unlike any other human experience, before she has had the experience of seeing and touching her newborn child, not only does she not know what it is like to have her child, she cannot know. Like the experience of seeing color for the first time, the experience of having a child is not projectable.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Instead, through hard lessons learned, I created a system of support that gave me the tools to gain awareness, reflect, and update my personal values and priorities <em>in real time</em>. I developed a love of subreddits where women got real about their changing identities and in the process validated my raw feelings, shared more openly with friends about my private struggles, looked for one couples therapist and ended up with two and kept both, and leaned hard on my coach who I first hired to make the most of a post-PhD sabbatical but who ended up supporting me in motherhood, moving continents, and starting a business all at the same time.</p>

<p><strong>So, what can you do if you’re in the stew?</strong></p>

<p>First, give yourself permission to be in it. Uncertainty is uncomfortable, but it’s also where clarity begins. The key is to create space for reflection and action, even when things feel messy. Here are three steps to get started:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Extrapolate, but Stay Flexible: Use what you know about yourself and what you’ve learned from others to make educated guesses about what you’ll need as a mother. Then, treat those guesses as hypotheses, not hard rules. Your priorities will evolve, and that’s okay.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Build Your Support System: Don’t try to figure it all out alone. Whether it’s a coach, a therapist, or a community of friends who’ve been through it, surround yourself with people who can help you navigate the shifts in your identity and career.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Take One Small Step: Start by identifying one thing you can do this week to move forward—whether it’s updating your resume, having a conversation with your partner, or simply journaling about what you want. You don’t need to have the perfect plan. Action creates momentum.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>If this resonates with you, and you’re ready to stop spinning your wheels and start building a career that supports the life you want, consistently, and with more ease and grace than doing it on your own, <a href="https://larissazhou.github.io/apply.html">apply for a strategy session</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="general" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Last week, I had two coaching conversations in which both women mentioned the words “motherhood” and “stew” in the same breath. What were the chances?!]]></summary></entry></feed>